<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xml:id="cha.remote" xml:lang="en"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Remote Administration</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    What is this chapter about?
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker></dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.conman">
  <title>ConMan &mdash; The Console Manager</title>
  <para>
   ConMan is a serial console management program designed to support a
   large number of console devices and simultaneous users. It supports:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     local serial devices
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     remote terminal servers (via the telnet protocol)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     IPMI Serial-Over-LAN (via FreeIPMI)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Unix domain sockets
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     external processes (for example, using 'expect' scripts for telnet,
     ssh, or ipmi-sol connections)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   ConMan can be used for monitoring, logging and optionally timestamping
   console device output.
  </para>
  <para>
   To install ConMan, run <literal>zypper in conman</literal>.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title><systemitem class="daemon">conmand</systemitem> Sends Unencrypted Data</title>
   <para>
    The daemon <systemitem class="daemon">conmand</systemitem> sends
    unencrypted data over the
    network and its connections are not authenticated. Therefore, it should
    be used locally only: Listening to the port
    <literal>localhost</literal>. However, the IPMI console does offer
    encryption. This makes <literal>conman</literal> a good tool for
    monitoring a large number of such consoles.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   Usage:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     ConMan comes with a number of expect-scripts. They can be found in the
     directory <filename>/usr/lib/conman/exec</filename>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Input to <literal>conman</literal> is not echoed in interactive mode.
     This can be changed by entering the escape sequence
     <literal>&amp;E</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When pressing <keycap function="enter"/> in interactive mode, no line
     feed is generated. To generate a line feed, press
     <keycombo><keycap function="control"/><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   For more information about options, see the man page of ConMan.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.genders">
  <title>Genders &mdash; Static Cluster Configuration Database</title>
  <para>
   Support for Genders has been added to the HPC module.
  </para>
  <para>
   Genders is a static cluster configuration database used for
   configuration management. It allows grouping and addressing sets of
   hosts by attributes and is used by a variety of tools. The Genders
   database is a text file which is usually replicated on each node in a
   cluster.
  </para>
  <para>
   Perl, Python, C, and C++ bindings are supplied with Genders, the
   respective packages provide man pages or other documentation describing
   the APIs.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create the Genders database, follow the instructions and examples in
   <filename>/etc/genders</filename> and check
   <filename>/usr/share/doc/packages/genders-base/TUTORIAL</filename>.
   Testing a configuration can be done with <literal>nodeattr</literal>
   (for more information, see <command>man 1 nodeattr</command>).
  </para>
  <para>
   List of packages:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>genders</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>genders-base</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>genders-devel</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>python-genders</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>genders-perl-compat</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>libgenders0</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <package>libgendersplusplus2</package>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.pdsh">
  <title>pdsh &mdash; Parallel Remote Shell Program</title>
  <para>
   <literal>pdsh</literal> is a parallel remote shell which can be used
   with multiple back-ends for remote connections. It can run a command on
   multiple machines in parallel.
  </para>
  <para>
   To install pdsh, run <command>zypper in pdsh</command>.
  </para>
  <para>
   On &slsa; 12, the back-ends <literal>ssh</literal>,
   <literal>mrsh</literal>, and <literal>exec</literal> are supported. The
   <literal>ssh</literal> back-end is the default. Non-default login methods
   can be used by either setting the <literal>PDSH_RCMD_TYPE</literal>
   environment variable or by using the <literal>-R</literal> command
   argument.
  </para>
  <para>
   When using the <literal>ssh</literal> back-end, it is important that a
   non-interactive (that is, passwordless) login method is used.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <literal>mrsh</literal> back-end requires the
   <literal>mrshd</literal> to be running on the client. The
   <literal>mrsh</literal> back-end does not require the use of reserved
   sockets. Therefore, it does not suffer from port exhaustion when
   executing commands on many machines in parallel. For information about
   setting up the system to use this back-end, see
  </para>
  <para>
   Remote machines can either be specified on the command line or
   <command>pdsh</command> can use a <filename>machines</filename> file
   (<filename>/etc/pdsh/machines</filename>), dsh (Dancer's shell) style
   groups or netgroups. Also, it can target nodes based on the currently
   running Slurm jobs.
  </para>
  <para>
   The different ways to select target hosts are realized by modules. Some
   of these modules provide identical options to <command>pdsh</command>.
   The module loaded first will win and consume the option. Therefore, we
   recommend limiting yourself to a single method and specifying this with
   the <literal>-M</literal> option.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <filename>machines</filename> file lists all target hosts one per
   line. The appropriate netgroup can be selected with the
   <literal>-g</literal> command line option.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following host-list plugins for <command>pdsh</command> are supported:
   <literal>machines</literal>, <literal>slurm</literal>,
   <literal>netgroup</literal> and <literal>dshgroup</literal>.
   Each host-list plugin is provided in a separate package. This avoids
   conflicts between command line options for different plugins which
   happen to be identical and helps to keep installations small and free
   of unneeded dependencies. Package dependencies have been set to prevent
   installing plugins with conflicting command options. To install one of
   the plugins, run:
  </para>
  <screen>zypper in pdsh-<replaceable>PLUGIN_NAME</replaceable></screen>
  <para>
   For more information, see the man page <command>pdsh</command>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.powerman">
  <title>PowerMan &mdash; Centralized Power Control for Clusters</title>
  <para>
   PowerMan allows manipulating remote power control devices (RPC) from a
   central location. It can control:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     local devices connected to a serial port
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     RPCs listening on a TCP socket
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     RPCs which are accessed through an external program
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The communication to RPCs is controlled by <quote>expect</quote>-like
   scripts. For a
   list of currently supported devices, see the configuration file
   <filename>/etc/powerman/powerman.conf</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To install PowerMan, run <command>zypper in powerman</command>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To configure it, include the appropriate device file for your RPC
   (<filename>/etc/powerman/*.dev</filename>) in
   <filename>/etc/powerman/powerman.conf</filename> and add devices and
   nodes. The device <quote>type</quote> needs to match the
   <quote>specification</quote> name in one
   of the included device files. The list of <quote>plugs</quote> used for
   nodes need to
   match an entry in the <quote>plug name</quote> list.
  </para>
  <para>
   After configuring PowerMan, start its service by:
  </para>
  <screen>systemctl start powerman.service</screen>
  <para>
   To start PowerMan automatically after every boot, run:
  </para>
  <screen>systemctl enable powerman.service</screen>
  <para>
   Optionally, PowerMan can connect to a remote PowerMan instance. To
   enable this, add the option <literal>listen</literal> to
   <filename>/etc/powerman/powerman.conf</filename>.
  </para>
  <important>
   <title>Unencrypted Transfer</title>
   <para>
    When connecting to a remote PowerMan instance, data is transferred
    unencrypted. Therefore, use this feature only if the network is
    appropriately secured.
   </para>
  </important>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.memkind">
  <title>memkind &mdash; Heap Manager for Heterogeneous Memory Platforms and Mixed Memory Policies</title>
  <para>
   The <literal>memkind</literal> library is a user-extensible heap manager
   built on top of <literal>jemalloc</literal> which enables control of
   memory characteristics and a partitioning of the heap between kinds of
   memory. The kinds of memory are defined by operating system memory
   policies that have been applied to virtual address ranges. Memory
   characteristics supported by <literal>memkind</literal> without user
   extension include control of NUMA and page size features.
  </para>
  <para>
   For more information, see:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     the man pages <literal>memkind</literal> and
     <literal>hbwallow</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://github.com/memkind/memkind"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://memkind.github.io/memkind/"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <note role="compact">
   <para>
    This tool is only available for x86-64.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.munge">
  <title><emphasis>munge</emphasis> Authentication</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis>munge</emphasis>
   allows users to connect as the same user from a machine to any other
   machine which shares the same secret key. This can be used to set up a
   cluster of machines between which the user can connect and execute
   commands without any additional authentication.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis>munge</emphasis> authentication is based on a single shared key.
   This key is
   located under <filename>/etc/munge/munge.key</filename>. At the installation
   time of the <package>munge</package> package an individual munge key is
   created from the random
   source <filename>/dev/urandom</filename>. This key has to be the same on
   all systems that should allow login to each other:
   To set up <literal>munge</literal> authentication on these machines copy
   the <emphasis>munge</emphasis> key from one machine (ideally a head node of
   the cluster)
   to the other machines within this cluster:
  </para>
  <screen>scp /etc/munge/munge.key root@<replaceable>NODE_N</replaceable>:/etc/munge/munge.key</screen>
  <para>
   Then enable and start the service munge on each machine that users are
   expected to log in to:
  </para>
  <screen>systemctl enable munge.service
systemctl start munge.service</screen>
  <para>
   If several nodes are installed, you must select and synchronize one key
   to all other nodes in the cluster. This key file should belong to the
   <systemitem class="username">munge</systemitem> user and must have the
   access rights <literal>0400</literal>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.mrsh">
  <title>mrsh/mrlogin &mdash; Remote Login Using <emphasis>munge</emphasis> Authentication</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis>mrsh</emphasis> is a set of remote shell programs using the
   <emphasis>munge</emphasis> authentication system instead of reserved ports
   for security.
  </para>
  <para>
   It can be used as a drop-in replacement for <literal>rsh</literal> and
   <literal>rlogin</literal>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To install <emphasis>mrsh</emphasis>, do the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If only the mrsh client is required (without allowing remote login to
     this machine), use: <command>zypper in mrsh</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To allow logging in to a machine, the server needs to be installed:
     <literal>zypper in mrsh-server</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To get a drop-in replacement for <command>rsh</command> and
     <command>rlogin</command>, run: <command>zypper in
     mrsh-rsh-server-compat</command> or <command>zypper in
     mrsh-rsh-compat</command>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   To set up a cluster of machines allowing remote login from each other,
   first follow the instructions for setting up and starting
   <emphasis>munge</emphasis> authentication in <xref linkend="sec2.installation.systemrole"/>.
   After <emphasis>munge</emphasis> has been successfully
   started, enable and start <command>mrlogin</command> on each machine on
   which the user will log in:
  </para>
  <screen>systemctl enable mrlogind.socket mrshd.socket
systemctl start mrlogind.socket mrshd.socket</screen>
  <para>
   To start mrsh support at boot, run:
  </para>
  <screen>systemctl enable munge.service
systemctl enable mrlogin.service</screen>
  <para>
   We do not recommend using <emphasis>mrsh</emphasis> when logged in as the
   user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>. This is disabled by
   default. To enable it anyway, run:
  </para>
  <screen>echo "mrsh" &gt;&gt; /etc/securetty
  echo "mrlogin" &gt;&gt; /etc/securetty</screen>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec.remote.ssh">
  <title>sshd config</title>
  <para>
   A paragraph of text.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
